cholesterol and heart disease why has
there been so much controversy and the
scientific consensus is that lowering
LDL cholesterol reduces heart attacks so
why are we still debating whether
cholesterol containing foods affect
blood cholesterol and how do eggs fit in
we look at those questions in this video
and the next
[Music]
the cholesterol controversy is over in
fact you can argue it was over a century
ago it seemed obvious in 1920. that high
cholesterol levels in the blood
infiltrating your artery walls was the
cause of coronary heart disease the
number one killer of men and women
confirmed as unequivocally as the
Revelation that blood circulated
throughout the body or that the
tuberculosis bacteria causes
tuberculosis
I've reviewed some of that evidence
previously in videos like how do we know
that cholesterol causes heart disease
and optimal cholesterol level
the question is why did it take so long
what is so puzzling is that why we have
to work so hard to sell the message
given what seems to be an unbeatable
amount of Hard Evidence many rejected
the cholesterol heart disease link
because so many patients were dying of
coronary heart disease despite so-called
perfectly normal cholesterol levels
of course as I've detailed before having
normal cholesterol levels in a society
where it's normal to drop dead of a
heart attack isn't exactly saying much
ideally we want to get our total
cholesterol well under 150 since having
high cholesterol levels in your blood is
thought of as the only direct
atherosclerotic risk factor all the
other things smoking high blood pressure
diabetes inactivity obesity just
exacerbate the damage caused by the high
cholesterol
another Factor may be the preoccupation
of cardiologists with all the new fancy
gadgets and procedures out there it's
like we train them to be highly skilled
high-tech fighter pilots to fight a war
but then sent them on some boring
preventive diplomatic mission
but the reasons maybe even more personal
than that
as an editorial in the Journal of the
American Heart Association asked nearly
50 years ago why do we pretend the cause
of heart disease is mysterious there is
no mystery as to why the incidence of
heart disease like that of lung disease
and of venereal disease sexually
transmitted disease continues to rise
for many decades after the cause is
established why because human beings
including Physicians are eager for
excuses not to face annoying facts and
so they continue to do things which are
agreeable but hazardous people tend to
reject new ideas even when they don't
impose any change in our way of life and
it's almost impossible for most men to
accept any suggestion and it might be
wise to give up agreeable habits such as
smoking unsafe sex or eating their
favorite foods this continuing challenge
is represented by a senior professor of
medicine who questioned whether an
alteration of diet would really affect
the course of heart disease these
professors know the facts the problem is
that they like so many patients will not
allow themselves to believe the message
eating rich food just means too much to
too many people even when it's our
gravest mortal threat
scientific consensus panels going back
decades established Beyond a reasonable
doubt that lowering LDL cholesterol
reduces the risk of heart attacks
consistent evidence unequivocally
establishes that LDL causes are number
one killer atherosclerotic
cardiovascular disease and what raises
LDL cholesterol saturated fat where is
cholesterol raising saturated fat found
the number one source is dairy number
two source is chicken then pastries pork
and burgers and it's not just saturated
fat dietary cholesterol has been known
as a dominant factor in the Genesis of
atherosclerosis since 1908 which is why
we should lower our intake of saturated
fats trans fats and dietary cholesterol
as much as possible this is consistent
with how our biology evolved extensive
evidence clearly indicates that a
plant-based diet was the traditional
eating pattern of our distant ancestors
and so dietary cholesterol intakes were
typically very low while at the same
time we were packing in whole plant
foods containing components like fiber
to help us eliminate cholesterol
where is dietary cholesterol coming from
now
overwhelmingly eggs with number two
Source chicken then beef Dairy and pork
so wait a second if the Institute of
medicine recommends that individuals
consume as little dietary cholesterol as
possible
presumably that would mean cutting out
foods like eggs entirely but does eating
cholesterol actually raise your blood
cholesterol
we'll find out
next
thank you